[Music]
Hello everyone.
Um I'm going to talk about uh AI tooling
in
intelligj and uh my talk will cover a
few stages starting from the completions
in line completions cloud completions
various AI actions uh chat modes in
intelligj reaching out to the agentic
tool that we just recently announced
juni and uh I will walk you through
through the phases. So um let me
actually start with uh the sharing the
screen. So I hope you can bring it up
now. U let's see. Yeah we are here. So I
have intelligj but we will start from
from the diagram. In fact I have a
little slide that's the only slide I
have. Everything else will be inside
intelligj. So those are the stages uh of
AI assistance inside the editors uh just
my creation. Uh I mean I I kind of I
haven't created all the tools but uh
it's it's something I came up with uh
for explaining the whole subject. So on
the left we have minimal assistance from
the tools where you have like uh uh very
minimal completions, single line
completions or single statement
completions inside the editor and
reaching out to
the most right uh end of the spectrum.
you have all this uh agentic mode uh
programming where you kind of lose uh or
stop tracking what kind of code you're
actually creating uh by by just uh
guiding the tool what kind of
functionality you want to generate and
we we start with a very basic one uh so
we start with the minimal um assistance
from the tooling uh let's see how it
looks like
inside So I have a spring boot
application. It's
uh it's a very minimal one. It's just
one controller. Uh there are a few
implementations of the algorithm
interface. Uh the they are just geometry
geometry filters basically. And uh let's
say I want to implement functionality
that will select the implementation
based on a configuration option. So
that's the scenario we're trying to
implement. And at the moment I assume
that I I'm really well aware of what
kind of code I want to write and I don't
need AI tool to actually write the code
for me. I want to do it myself. I want
to stay in the control. So uh what kind
of code would I write here? So maybe a
function function that
selects select uh
algorithm by uh a property that is
injected from the configuration and
that's going to be something like this.
Uh there's the dollar. I got to type a
property name. I'm going to type and
then property parameter name should be
type uh of type string string. And well
I as you see I'm not really getting a
lot of assistance by the AI
yet. Uh that's going to be a
bean right there. And that's going to be
uh an algorithm. So we first time we see
some completion happening right here at
the end of the line because uh what is
happening right now as I type there is a
local model working inside the IDE uh
provided by a plug-in called full line
completion that looks at the code
skipping the comments that it sees above
the cursor in the same file and tries to
come up with suggestion. In fact, I can
visualize what is happening. Let me
complete this line with an internal with
an internal tool
uh that I have installed for myself. So
there are stats happening. This is
something I installed just to visualize
for for this demo to visualize what is
happening when I hit the uh buttons and
uh the ID is working on providing the uh
different suggestions. So uh as I type
here I I know exactly what code I want
to type right. want to check for the
value of the string and uh if it matches
some sort of a value I would return u a
class or a type instance. So
return and as you can see uh on the
bottom right uh the model has calculated
that with probability of 36% the next
statement that should satisfy my
requirement is going to be when with the
type subject and it also renders it in
the editor. That's cool cool information
for me to check how the u AI completion
works. But let's see how how it works
like uh for the next statements I'm
going to type. Uh as you can see uh it's
it suggest it found some suggestion by
the model that is working on my machine
right now. Uh but this suggestion
doesn't seem to be relevant. It might be
red code. it might be
um the like irrelevant code maybe even
whatever the model generates. So for
this kind of workflow where I'm exactly
aware what kind of code I want to write
I just need very fast completions to um
to help me uh w with the task that I'm
currently working on and not to get in
the way. That's the most annoying thing
when the tool is getting in the way and
that is why we are ra we would rather
not show you any completion than show
you something incorrect or something
that is hallucinated. So if I continue
uh let's say
quick is one of the values I want to
get. I can see that uh the model is
generating something
uh and quick is the model
uh I want to get an instance on the next
line it already suggests something that
is relevant and uh the code is not read
so I can accept it. So that's the uh
that's
the kind of very minimal that's the very
start of the AI assisted programming
inside uh intellig idea and it's
configurable. We have options uh for
inline completions where you can enable
or disable full line completions based
on the language and download the
relevant models. Uh I currently have all
of them downloaded. Therefore, uh they
just display as checkboxes. But normally
you would have like a download download
button there. Um we also have another
step in in the story where we can uh say
that we we know what we want to get but
we are too lazy to type and uh we we
want to get uh larger code snippets from
from the models as an assistance. So we
can enable the cloud completion
suggestions. They can suggest full
snippets of code. Uh there there are
limits of course it will not generate
like 1,000 lines of code but it will
generate sensible
um code snippets that you can accept
partially uh token by token or line by
line. And it has a few uh levels of
configurations where you want um the
filter that works inside the ID to
filter out more to allow uh less red
code or let's say less creative code
that then you would select the focused
mode for this completion or you want to
get more creative and uh you are fine of
getting some interesting code snippets
from the model. I I have currently
enabled the balance mode. Uh let's see
how it works. I feel adventurous today.
So I have enabled uh the cloud
completion and let's see how it behaves
with the same uh scenario that I just
had. Uh so previously as I said the full
line completion would ignore the
comments. So it would only look at the
code snippets. Uh but here I am I
already added a comment of a function
that I want to write. uh and the cloud
completion would account for that. So if
I just type it here it already sees that
well there are implementations of the
algorithm there is a interface we are in
the context of spring boot application
uh we want to read a configuration
option and so on and it comes up with
this uh full complete correct uh code
snippet where I could you know now
accept either partially
Um either
partially let's see uh I have something
with my uh keyboard right now or just
completely uh accepting those snippets
as is. Maybe I don't want some snippets,
some part of the snippet and uh I would
rather throw an exception if uh if I
don't match any of the values in from
the configuration and uh yeah currently
you can see that Melum is the completion
provider in the diagnostics right here
in in the bottom left and Melum is our
open-source uh completion model that we
are we we recently open sourced uh to
the community you can download it and
experiment with that as well. So as you
can see we have two levels already of
completions where where I know exactly
what I want to do and I want to control
every statement or I can lose the ants
up a little bit and uh uh I'm fine with
the completion generating various code
snippets like in multiple lines of code.
Let's go further. Uh the next level is
in editor generation with minimalistic
prompts. Meaning that you are still uh
focused on the code that you're
currently writing. Assume um well we we
can have something else here. We can uh
let's see we can uh let's try generate
uh generating a function that would
uh
maybe split a list of values for us
split a function function or a utility
function uh to split a list of elements
into a list of lists of
elements by
an example element. So this would invoke
a local code generation and it's kind of
similar to the uh snippet completion
that we just saw. The difference is that
the completion would run or generate the
code in the place of the cursor but
inline code generation would actually
span uh across the file. It might add
imports. It might change the function
names. It might split functions. It
might generate some additional
components for for this to work.
uh and of course it's also double
checked with uh for for the red code for
the relevance and so on. So now now we
have the patch right in the in the code.
We can do some follow-ups here to
correct our uh requirements to the
generated code. Maybe what I see here is
not uh exactly corresponding to what I
want. Uh maybe I want to add extra
constraints or I can just accept it. Uh,
of course further on I can either
regenerate this code somehow say that I
don't want functional style or vice
versa I want it to be mutable uh or call
start calling the AI actions and the AI
actions actually start getting you out
of the current screen uh current file
and uh maybe generate some code outside
of that file. So for instance we we can
ask it to generate unit
tests. So currently what is happening
the the AI assistant uh matched the name
or the the suffix of the file uh that we
that we used to call the action from and
it created a relevant name for the test
file and created a few test cases for me
to
uh to satisfy the functionality that I
just generated for for that function. As
you can see, we already loosening our
control uh a little bit more. We are not
focusing on a single line of code. We
are not focusing even on a local snippet
of code. We are now uh generating the
code in the v in different places of the
file and even in different files. So
let's uh accept that. I'm not sure if
the tests would fail or not. Let's
assume that some of them should fail,
some of them probably will
pass. Uh but uh currently our goal is
not to test the code. The goal is to
explain at which stage are we. So we
generated the code inside the editor. In
fact, we can move on and uh look at the
chat now. So from this point on we are
getting out of the local file. We are
shifting our focus out of the uh editor.
As you can see the tests uh some of the
tests failed. Some of the tests uh
didn't fail but uh uh we we we we can
take the different flow and start fixing
them and asking the AI assistant how to
fix them. That's that's not in focus
right now. So let's get ourselves into
the chat. How can we do that? For
instance, the uh function that we just
generated this one, we can ask the uh AI
assistant to start doing something with
this snippet of code like start chat
using the
selection. We can either take the full
file there or just a
function and ask uh the assistant to do
something with with this code. uh like
transform it or maybe test it somehow
differently, suggest something. There is
now uh a dilemma, not really a dilemma
but there is a uh one important uh fact
you have to account for is that by
default the chat would not look into the
whole project, right? It we just asked
it to do something with a little snippet
of code. So we already take this action
to isolate it. Uh but we can choose to
tell it to look at the whole code base.
Please uh when whatever action I uh ask
you to do, please scan the project for
the relevant for the relevance of my
query and maybe populate the context
with additional information from the
source code depending what what will I
ask for. So maybe I will ask to rewrite
rewrite this code uh in
imperative
style. Uh the uh what will happen the
chat will retransform my query ask the
platform if there are any relevant
resources that we can add into the
context. Currently there were no
additional uh files attached only the
selection and the current file actually
and then we just got the response. So at
this point we are um at the position of
uh kind we are kind of an agent right
now. We are the agent. We take the
decision what kind of code do we want to
integrate back into the project. uh what
uh tests we have to run to assure that
the code is correct and so on. So there
is a an extra mode for figuring out uh
or automating integration of the code
generated uh model generated code back
into the project. We are currently in
the chat mode but we could have
automated that as well. So there is a
beta feature. I'm not going to run that
uh at the moment because we want to get
to aentic workflows quicker. But at this
point, I can just tell uh the AI
assistant to integrate the code
correctly and uh it will display me the
diff that uh applies applies the code
snippet. All right.
So uh when we are no actually I will
take you to the editor mode and uh just
to quickly demonstrate what could
happen. Uh so we we're going to switch
into codebase mode. Uh we're going to
tell the chat that it can observe
whatever uh we have in the project. Yes.
Sorry Anton. Um this is super exciting
and and and and just wanted to flag very
very quickly that there's a lot of
people who are asking you a ton of very
relevant question and we are jumping in
one minute with the next talk. I have
tried to curate like some of these
questions. So I'm just going to in the
next one minute if you can try to answer
multiple questions at once. So at least
these were the most relevant. Um okay.
So first of all, we've had a couple of
people wanting to ask you uh and I think
you mentioned it throughout your talk of
like what libraries were used, but uh
could you restate uh what Jet Brains
like AI assistant and like Juny like
what stack is it based on? What
languages is it based on? And a very
quick followup like how does Juny
understand like the legacy system and
like the constraints uh for each uh
enterprise or like a company or project?
Right. So we have two uh plugins. I have
been showing only the part for the
assistant and I just executed the query
for Juny to run on the screen while I'm
answering the question. Uh Juny provides
completion. Oh not Juny sorry AI
assistant provides uh completion. the
model
selector you you can chat with your
project and uh you are the agent who
decides what kind of code to integrate
and what tests to run. Juny in contrast
just automates all that for you. So it
will iterate on the uh on the problem
that you have asked for. Like for
instance in in this workflow that I just
uh started I asked Juny to implement the
persistence layer which means that it
will span the the code changes will span
across the entire project starting from
the controller to services configuration
files build files maybe for adding the
uh
different uh additional
uh libraries and so on. So the stack uh
you mean the implementation probably
then uh it's all implemented in cotlin
of course because most of the uh plugins
that we build and like we we develop for
intelligj platform they are built with
cotlin
uh it works for any languages but for
juni specifically what we want to do is
to be able to integrate with the
platform specific or technology specific
speific tools. Meaning if I generate
code for Java, I should be able to run
the Java compiler or Java llinter or
some Java build tool like Maven or
Gradle uh and get uh maybe run the
tests. So I need to integrate with uh
testr runner and so on and that is
technology specific right. So uh for
Juny we do that for Juny it depends what
kind of technology you use in the
project. Uh however code generation
doesn't depend on that. So even if Juny
does not support some technology like
running Python tests for inside
intelligj maybe because it's implemented
for PyCharm. uh Juni is still able to
generate the code that you ask for uh
even though it's not supported inside
the platform. Uh for instance, you you
may want to generate some C++ code in uh
in inside and there is no C++ tooling by
default. So that's possible. Wonderful.
Thank you so much for for explaining all
that, Anton. And yeah, like I think a
lot of us started coding with Jet Brains
and we're just all super excited that
Juni is out. Uh so yeah, excited to see
where all that is going to go. But yeah,
fantastic talk. Super cool session. I
think everybody really really enjoyed
it. So thank you so much Anton. Thank
you.